Grace Noll Crowell papers, Inclusive: 1904-1958, undated, Bulk: 1921-1955, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Grace Noll Crowell papers
Inclusive: 1904-1958, undated, Bulk: 1921-1955, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3359
Crowell, Grace Noll
4 document boxes
The Grace Noll Crowell papers contain scrapbooks, correspondence, photographs, and a movie advertisement printing plate, the majority being related to her family and her career as a poet.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Grace Noll Crowell was born in Inland, Iowa, on 1877 October 31 and graduated in 1901 with her Bachelor of Arts from German-English College in Wilton, Iowa. She married Norman H. Crowell on 1901 September 4 and had three sons, Dean, Reid, and Norton. Crowell’s family moved to Wichita Falls, Texas, in 1917, and to Dallas in 1919.
Crowell began writing poetry while immobile after giving birth to her first child. Her first written poem was “The Marshland,” and she published her first poetry book in October 1925, White Fire, winning first prize from the Texas Poetry Society. Many of her poems were published in magazines and newspapers, clippings of which appear in this collection. They illustrate various parts of life, especially homemaking, motherhood, family, holidays, and religious themes.
Crowell won numerous awards and honors for her poetry, including being named Poet Laureate of Texas in 1935, winning the Golden Scroll Medal of Honor in 1938 as National Honor Poet, and being chosen as honorary chancellor of the National Federation of State Poetry Societies in 1965. She was also chosen as American Mother of the Year by the Golden Rule Foundation in 1938. Baylor University awarded her an honorary doctorate in 1940.
Crowell had a full career of writing and publishing poetry, prose, and stories, amounting to over thirty-five published books. The most well-known books of poetry are White Fire (1925) Silver in the Sun (1928), Miss Humpety Comes to Tea (1929), Flame in the Wind (1930), Songs for Courage (1935), Light of the Years (1936), This Golden Summit (1937), and Songs of Hope (1938). Grace N. Crowell died in Dallas on 31 March 1969 and is buried at Hillcrest Mausoleum.
Scope and Content
The Grace Noll Crowell papers begin in 1904 and end in 1958. The largest series is made up of scrapbooks, mainly containing Crowell’s poems, other poems, and newspaper and magazine clippings of stories on Crowell. The second largest series contains photographs of her family and colleagues at the German English College. The collection also contains correspondence, including a manuscript of “The Glowing Word,” legal documents, invitations and booklets, a Storm Lake, Iowa, newspaper with a poem by Crowell’s husband, and a separate series for a movie advertisement printing plate.
Arrangement
The Grace Noll Crowell papers did not have any discernible organization prior to this finding aid, apart from scrapbooks and photographs being grouped together. There were several different existing inventories. Folder titles were changed and the collection was organized into series based on type of material. Scrapbooks were dismantled and placed in folders in order to preserve the pages.
The Grace Noll Crowell papers are presently arranged in four series: I. Scrapbooks, II. Personal Papers, III. Photographs, and IV. Metal Printing Plate.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3359. Acquired 2000-06-29
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Painting 43. Fine Arts collection. - Texas. - People. - Grace Noll Crowell
Related references
Flowers, Betty S. "Crowell, Grace Noll." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2014 April 21.
Plumb, Beatrice. Grace Noll Crowell: The Poet and the Woman. New York: Harper, 1938.
U.S. Bureau of the Census. 1900 United States Census, s.v. “Grace G. Noll,” Spencer Township, Clay, Iowa. Accessed 2014 April 21.
U.S. Bureau of the Census. 1940 United States Census, s.v. “Grace N. Crowell,” Dallas, Texas. Accessed 2014 April 21.
Index Terms
Places
Dallas (Tex.) -- History.; Texas -- History -- 20th century.
Subjects
American poetry -- Texas -- 20th century.; American poetry -- Texas.; Christian poetry, American -- Texas.; Poets laureate -- Texas.; Religious poetry, American.; Women and literature -- United States -- History -- 20th century.
Genres
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Scrapbooks, 1904-1958; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains scrapbooks mainly containing Crowell’s poems, other poems of inspiration, and newspaper and magazine clippings of stories on Crowell.
  - Crowell Poems and Collected Poems (1 of 3), circa 1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Crowell Poems and Collected Poems (2 of 3), circa 1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Crowell Poems and Collected Poems (3 of 3), circa 1907 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Crowell Poems and Collected Poems (1 of 5), 1904-1922, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Crowell Poems and Collected Poems (2 of 5), 1904-1922, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Crowell Poems and Collected Poems (3 of 5), 1904-1922, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Crowell Poems and Collected Poems (4 of 5), 1904-1922, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Crowell Poems and Collected Poems (5 of 5), 1904-1922, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Crowell Poems and Stories (1 of 3), circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Crowell Poems and Stories (2 of 3), circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Crowell Poems and Stories (3 of 3), circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (1 of 6), 1924-1927, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (2 of 6), 1924-1927, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (3 of 6), 1924-1927, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (4 of 6), 1924-1927, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (5 of 6), 1924-1927, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (6 of 6), 1924-1927, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (1 of 5), 1921-1930, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (2 of 5), 1921-1930, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (3 of 5), 1921-1930, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (4 of 5), 1921-1930, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (5 of 5), 1921-1930, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (1 of 3), 1925-1936, 1948-1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (2 of 3), 1925-1936, 1948-1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Crowell and Collected Poems, Clippings, and Correspondence (3 of 3), 1925-1936, 1948-1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1925-1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1939-1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings (1 of 4), 1929-1941 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings (2 of 4), 1929-1941 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings (3 of 4), 1929-1941 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings (4 of 4), 1929-1941 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Personal Papers, 1931, undated; 2
  General condition: Good.
  This series contains correspondence, including a manuscript of “The Glowing Word,” legal documents, invitations and booklets, and a Storm Lake, Iowa, newspaper with a publication by Crowell’s husband.
  - The Glowing Word, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1902-1944 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Storm Lake Pilot Tribune, 26 February 1931 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1913-1955; 3
  This series includes photographs of Grace Noll Crowell’s family and photographs from German-English College.
  - Family (1 of 4), 1937-1955, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Family (2 of 4), 1937-1955, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Family (3 of 4), 1937-1955, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Family (4 of 4), 1937-1955, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Family, 1915, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Family (1 of 3), undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Family (2 of 3), undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Family (3 of 3), undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - German-English College, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Family (1 of 2), 1913, 1914 or 1915, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Family (2 of 2), 1913, 1914 or 1915, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Family: Oversized Materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Printing Plate, 1933; 4
  This series contains a printing plate for three films from 1933, “Female,” “Hoop-La,” and “Man’s Castle.”
  - Movie Advertisement, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 15)